hello everyone it is june 16th 2022 and
it's meeting seven of the active
textbook textbook group cohort one
we're in our second discussion of
chapter three
today we'll be looking at the questions
that haven't been addressed so the ones
without thumbs
and
also it's not too late to add more
questions or to upvote questions
and then additionally
since the
math learning group has been
quite active
in providing synchronous
affordances for conversation around
some of the background on the math as
well as some aspects of the equations
that we'll go through today
and also even to like applications of
the math and developing notebooks and
such
we'll
take a look at the math
in our
move through chapter 3.
before we go to the questions does
anyone
have anything that they just want to
like remark on chapter 3
ali and then anyone else
yeah
well last week i talked about how i
changed my mind about these
bottom up and top down characterizations
of low road and
high road respectively after reading
chapter three
but it turns out that they are in fact
bottom half and top down approaches
after all you see
i came across this uh in my opinion
undeservedly lesser known piece of
beautiful beautiful writing by carl
fristan
which explicitly argues for such
characterizations and
the philosophical importance
of this distinction
it's called beyond the desert landscape
and it's inconspicuously hidden
in this book andy clark and his critics
so
i i'd like to quote um a couple of
sentences from this
writing
uh well
he writes code
the high road stands in for a top-down
approach that starts by asking
fundamental questions about the
necessary properties
things must possess if they exist using
mathematical variational principles one
can then show that existence is an
embodied exchange of a creature
with its environment that necessarily
entails predictive processing as one
aspect of the self-evidencing mechanics
the low road is the purpose the agenda
established by
is the
is to pursue the agenda established by
content hellholtz and generalize in a
bottom-up way the capacity for inference
and prediction to see how far it takes
us in understanding embodied exchange
with the environment so if anyone likes
to
gain a deeper understanding about these
conceptual um characterizations i highly
highly recommend
this
chapter of this book and and quite
unusually for a frist in writing uh it
also lacks
any mathematical formalism it doesn't
include a single mathematical equation
there
thank you
yeah in a recent stream we also talked
about the desert landscape and clark's
concern
was that
we might do away with what populates our
implicitly assumed to be rich ecosystems
of psychology philosophy
and so on with important ecosystem
players
like
goals
and so the fear or concern was that we
might be in a quiet and desert landscape
if we replace
some of these again implicitly or
explicitly stated to be rich constructs
like goals and we're like well it's just
distribution matching
then we've made some sort of like a
desert monoculture and that would be um
dip operate of
what
what what does clark say to his desert
living critics
um all right
if anyone else
has a thought they can raise their hand
otherwise we can look at the questions
okay
so this first
question
if one defines preferred states as
expected states one can say living
organisms must minimize the surprise of
their sensory observations
i'm not clear on the ontology here
is it that preference is the same as
expectation or that formally we can use
them in the same equation
is that an ontological claim
and is the free energy in physics an
analogy or an ontological assertion
about how things really are
so one starting place
was uh i i found the slide and so wanted
to highlight it this was in
free energy
a user's guide which was live stream
number 37
um the slides will be probably a little
bigger
um
it's worth restating just how unusual it
is to interpret p as a measure of both
probabilities and preferences
they both start with p though
there's nothing wrong with treating a
distribution as a measure of preferences
because distributions can have different
interpretations
but what's unorthodox and in need of
justification is giving the same
mathematical term
two different interpretations within the
same equation
they then add some more details
that unpack a little bit about how
it is the case that the same
term p
can be utilized
uh as
uh
both a probability
and a preference
and then they even extended it into a
third p
the ph fitness
where
by
allowing your probabilities and your
preferences to converge to reduce the
divergence between those two
distributions
then
fitness is achieved
and so
they provided a
restatement
of the way that that is implemented
and then
uh highlighted an additional
grounding or interpretive line
so that's
at least one part of that question
and also to look towards the equations
it's
something that we'll be able to
have very clear answers for and thanks
to the work of ali and blue and
others who have been
annotating equations
so for example in equation 3.1
or we can look at like box one
equation one
which is like a markov blanket
definition
in the description fields
we have a natural language
description
and then the terms that are used
in the description
are those that are referenced using
variables
so that will help us
translate across natural language of
different human languages
the discrete and continuous time
formalisms which we're going to explore
in this textbook
also
identical or isomorphic or related
formalisms in other papers which
sometimes are using the same notation
letters
but not always
but we could have another column for
first in 2019
and here's first in 2013
and then there's a conversation to be
had about where they align or don't and
that's the kind of annotation work that
somebody can engage in from the
publications and that also helps us
connect it to the the programmatic
implementations
like in active block rinse
or in other scripts
so that even that we can promote
norms and practices around variable
naming
in math
and in programming
but also where there is divergences or
differences which are important for
innovating and evolving the norms
we can also map them pretty coherently
so all the equations for three
can be um
red
naturally
so we discussed this a lot in the math
group and and again a lot of people
contributed to this
with one of the goals or
functions being that whenever we are
going to bring up an equation
like if there's a question about
equation 3.1
we can just
briefly
read
the current state of the description
because whether you're super familiar
with the letters and variables and how
they're concatenated
or whether it's just like a first pass
on your
seeing this equation
everybody will benefit when we align our
regime of attention to actually what it
says
and then that will help us do many many
other things
but to return back to this
question
um
does anyone
want to raise their hand and give a
thought
on
the relationship between preference and
expectation
ontological claims
about preference
and its relationship with expectation
and more generally
is the free energy
something that isn't
analogy
or mathematical
isomorphism or an equation that rhymes
or is it also an assertion
it's an equation that rhymes
what makes you say that no not just
because
just because it's cute that's all
uh i just joined the conversation but
preference and expectation i wouldn't
think they were
at all referring to the same thing
i mean expectation is a mathematical
operator
preference is
a statement
yes
expectation is used in multiple ways
it can refer to
predictions about the mean or the mode
or other attributes of a future time
point like i'm expecting uh you know
what are you expecting to happen on next
monday
right right also expectation can refer
and that's how it's used with the fancy
e
to refer to the expected value
of a distribution which for a gaussian
is
the mode
in the center of the symmetric peak
and that doesn't need to be about a
future time point
that can just be the expectation
[Music]
of the height of the classroom right now
does it's not saying that's what we're
expecting it to be in a year
as it might be used conversationally but
it's referring to just like the average
of a distribution
right
mathematically it's an operator and
verbally it can be
a prediction or a desire or something
yes
and then yeah again in 37 and elsewhere
um
it'll be worth returning to this again
and again because it's one of the
essential
architectural
decisions in active inference
that enable
it's
part of the necessity and sufficiency
complex i don't know whether this is one
one the whole
um meat of it but it's part of what
allows
the dispensal of like an explicit reward
term
like
a homeostatic reinforcement reward
driven learner
would be like i'm more rewarded by being
in my homeostatic range
and then there needs to be this
architecture around well how are we
going to pursue reward
alternatively
an organism
trying to maintain homeostasis
realism or us modeling an organism that
is maintaining homeostasis
instrumentalism
we can just say
it expects to be
in the range that conversationally we're
going to describe as a preference
how do we know we put the animal in the
room and it's spending a lot of its time
on this warmer side
it prefers to be there
we also expect it to be there
we're less surprised when we see it
there
so then
it's possible to as they write here
interpret that
p
location distribution in the room for
the animal that we're observing or the
temperature distribution for the body in
the homeostatic context
as being a probability density
over temperatures over locations
as well as
reflecting the preferences
not the qualia or the phenomenology or
anything like too far out about what it
means to prefer where preferences arise
from whether they're fixed or learned in
the model all these like many many
trails that can come out of that
but just at this like
essential layer
we don't need to interpolate a reward
term
between what is expected
and what is preferred
any other comments from someone yes eric
and then anyone else
yeah i just um just to remark on that
it seems you're still not removing the
free variable of what the preference of
the
agent organism is
you're just holding it you're putting in
a different place so that you can
use it in this unified equation
but
you still have this
it's a pre variable okay what what do
you want to do okay i'm going to call
that an expectation and that's what i'm
going to
try to drive for when i uh optimize my
my variational
free energy
but it in that sense it's um it's kind
of a convenience or it's a trick it's a
little bit of an unnatural act i don't
know like that way i think of it for a
purpose
but
there's nothing
um
you haven't solved any other problem and
you know the deeper problem of
what should the organism attempt to
achieve the goals
yes
thanks ali
uh well
i think it also
might be quite helpful to refer back to
chapter 2 uh on page 36 i think yeah
page 36 uh
[Music]
i think
well here
they have actually
distinguished between the term
prediction and exactly yes here the term
prediction and expectation quite
explicitly
in terms of equation 2.6 so
okay
so let's look at equation 2.6
okay a few of the were all um
that we don't have the third line
um
fully described
but just here's the third line what does
this speak to with respect to
preferences and expectations
but here the preference actually is in
the second term the
callback library divergence here yeah
and
so
it's actually
inherent in the second term and the
expectation expected ambiguity
uh as it speaks for itself is the first
term so
we have here
uh
the risk is defined as the divergence
between the pre the preference and the
states so
i think that we can see the preference
in this equation as well
one note here is like that this g is
equal to the first the seconds
and um
this line
but one way that um we can understand
the relationship of the second and the
third line
is like they're very similar the first
term is identical
here
the only difference is that instead of a
y
we see an x
and so this is like x being the hidden
state and y being the observation
in the case where it's a fully
observable markov process
then the outcomes and the hidden states
are going to be like equal uncertainty
about them
because
in that case it's functionally that the
hidden states are observables
however if there's any amount of
ambiguity like the a matrix between the
hidden state and the observable
then there's always going to be more
uncertainty about the hidden state
relative to the observable
and then
importantly on both sides
there's a conditioning vertical line on
policy selection
and so that is what prevents us from
getting into like well what if it's 95
correct or 96 or 97 correct or any of
these sort of like model
diminishing returns debates
it's a
functional that's calculated for each
policy
that have been been
um possible of composing given the
affordances a policy is just a sequence
of actions so if there's four movement
affordances
there's four policies of time depth one
there's 16 policies of time depth two
and so on and for whatever in this
discrete formalism
finite set of policies there are
they're evaluated here
and then
there's a policy selection
that could choose the lowest
expected free energy or it could
proportionally choose from them with
different kinds of waiting and so on but
this is comparing the relative expected
ambiguity and risk
conditioned upon different specific
policies
and there's a process by which those
specific policies can be enumerated
and then this is a process by which
they're going to be evaluated
and then there's a policy selection by
which they're selected
so
organisms that fail to do this
adequately enough will be dissipated
or
systems
whether it's just um a molecular system
or some other kind of statistical system
that failed to do this well enough
to remain being that kind of thing
are not amenable to repeated
measurements
they are not that thing but things that
remain being that thing
for the time horizon of observations
will be selecting policies that are
consistent with this
can ask a question about this yeah about
this equation here
um
say let the second line
so i would have expected
so first of all see the the preferences
is not really spelled out very much in
this chapter and i don't know where it
will be
um
but um i would have expected something
more like preferences given
observations like you know the
observations of
what's what's happening in the world
that we can measure that's observation
why
and how does that
and how does that fit with my
preferences so what i want to optimize
is my preference
the achievement of my preferences
as
delivered by the observations
now i understand in that
that in that second equation
you're going to do a divergence
between observations the uh the tildes
the y tildes so you can't flip around p
of c given y tilde there
so
can somebody explain to me how this all
fits together then how do you achieve
preferences
under that equation
all give one
um thought and and i absolutely agree to
the first point which is like c is just
like
i don't even know if it's
described in this chapter
like it just
34 i think
34.
uh let me check it again
um
i mean there is this
yeah he says basically
parameter includes preferences but that
includes parameter yeah and also if
you're uh if you go to uh section 7.4 i
think
yeah in that section
it is untangled why these two parameters
are related and how these two parameters
are related to each other
section
yeah yeah i mean
like
there's there's that's like multiple
scales of where the information is not
provided
before when it needs to be provided
which is like this i
have made as just a helpful diagram of
the partially observable markov decision
process
which is c is the preferences and it
influences how g
evaluates policies which are generated
from affordances over a given time
horizon policies intervene upon how
hidden states change in the world
and there's there's more in different
readings but to return to um eric's
question and then again anyone with the
raised hand so
the question was whether we're comparing
outcomes
or states
how does this second term
help us realize our preference
well
when is the kl we're trying to minimize
g of pi
better policies have a lower score it's
like um golf i guess
or you could add negatives and make it
higher um and also just
it's an interesting note like climbing
mount improbable biologists often think
about the fitness peak
and climbing to fitness peaks
whereas for a physicist it's often
framed and also like
computer science gradient descending
and local minima global minima
but they're
just
actually like
the same landscape with some negative
signs
so the kl divergence and here we're
trying to minimize
if it's zero
that would mean like
we are perfectly realizing
our preference
so
let's just say that there's two policies
that we're comparing between
and one of them is going to perfectly
realize our preferences the other one
isn't so we have like pi one and pi two
and we're going to be calculating the kl
divergence of the outcomes
that we're expecting under the
variational distribution queue under
policy one
and under policy two
so if policy one is going to perfectly
realize our our uh if the outcomes of
policy one are expected to perfectly
realize our preferences
this term will be zero
whereas if policy two is going to
be expected to result in
an outcome distribution that's not
aligned with our preferences it doesn't
get penalized here
this is just evaluated as a as a value
nor does it get penalized here
because in this case of fixed
preferences that's also not changing
as we iterate through policies however
there would be a divergence that would
be non-zero like all divergences are
between the inferior policy and the
superior policy so by iterating over the
finite set of policies that we have
taking this term
and just leaving to the side for now
only the kl divergence
this will lead us to select policies
that can be expected to bring alignment
between the observations conditioned on
policy and our preferences preferred
outcome distribution
thank you that's very helpful so just to
kind of say that slightly differently is
given your preferences that's that
that's going to imply some outcomes
and what you're trying to do with that
kl that vergence is trying to get the
policy that will achieve those outcomes
so
if we
expect and prefer to be within the
homeostatic thermal range
and then the two policies in the
snowstorm are add the jacket or remove
the jacket
which one of those
are expected to
have the minimum divergence between us
being in the homeostatic range
and then the policy conditioned
expected outcomes
i'm going to have less divergence it
doesn't even mean you're going to live
it just means i'm going to have less
divergence by having the jacket on in
the snowstorm than by taking it off
which is going to move the expected
outcome distribution further from the
preference distribution which here is
fixed
but doesn't have to be fixed
okay
so we have several
um is anyone
here the person who has written any of
these questions so then we can just go
to that one
lyle
yes
there we go i think i'm i think i went
in here
okay so yeah i uh i wrote the one
that
is referring to the living organisms and
the question about
to what extent are these techniques
valuable in
what i would call social systems of
wide-ranging sorts
and
i know that this book at the outset
limits itself to
biological systems at least that's my
recollection from the introduction but
uh it just seems obvious to me that
this would have much broader
applicability
i'm curious what
sort of what the state of that is
well
um
do i hesitate to put anyone on the spot
john would you
give a first response there while i add
some resources
yeah
my first thought on that is
um
obviously
our civilization is struggling
and um
and civilizations have failed in the
past who collapsed
so it's not necessarily the case that
every social structure or societal
structure
is actually performing
functional active inference
but if we were a
highly functional organism if societies
were a highly functional organism
we would be doing something like active
inference and learning from learning
from our mistakes and
making sure that we put ourselves in a
environment that uh that is sustainable
and all that kind of stuff
so that what my first thought is
i think that all of this is applicable
to societal systems
but it doesn't necessarily mean that
any existing societal systems actually
perform functional
active inference
yeah
thanks it's almost like saying
uh
okay we're studying the penguins and
their thermostats and homeostats
this model could be parameterized to fit
a thriving or a failing society along
various different dimensions
and so in the sense that this is like a
linear aggression that can capture
failing as well as succeeding societies
yes the nested markov blanket formalism
has qualitatively but increasingly
quantitatively been applied and there's
multiple like startups and applications
that are explicitly pursuing this angle
it's been brought up for several years
now and um
in 2020 several of us wrote about it
being applied to remote teams and
organizations
and communities i can add these links to
decentralized science as a system and
ecosystem so
yes
people have started to sketch that
continent out
and there's a lot more to understand
what do you think lyle
yeah
i think that's that makes a ton of sense
i think uh obviously i guess the way i
was thinking about the question is
not so much whether
to what extent social systems do this
because social systems so you could take
two points of view one is you could say
social systems are behaving cognitively
in the ways
that we're
discussing
in other words they're
they're our preferred states that are
driving behavior now we could say
those preferred states are the wrong
states for whatever reasons
but
so so there's there's a question you
know between what we actually you know
as in any particular social system was
actually happening which i would argue
could be described through this
technique
or what they should be doing which we
could also describe through this
technique right so i think
i think it's important to have that
distinction and there's a really long
history of using dynamic systems models
to explore
those questions especially in the
business context so that's mostly how i
made my living through the
through the decades
so
though
that that you know sort of you know as
is to be or would prefer to be
sort of questioned it just seems like
this technique it would potentially be a
significant advance over the tools
in that space that currently exists
which are primarily
things like system dynamics and
agent-based modeling stuff like that
but this would seem to have the
potential to look at things as they are
why is it broken and what we might do
yes so
i've added several other
uh references it's important and the
book again is like
if it's describing the linear model then
there's the applications of a linear
model and
as people and as john brought up like
many times in this
uh series of live streams that we did
together with four with just the two of
us with john leading through
basically the entire thread of this
discussion of three papers and then two
more group discussions
there's been recent work on like scripts
by mao and colleagues
with a strong and a weak script
formalization like a strong script being
when the norms are practiced like in a
ritualistic way like reading from a
script versus the looser script concept
which could include just norms and
social praxis
and then more recently their modeling
work using pi mdp
to talk about epistemic communities
and then
some of the very earliest
live streams that we did were on
narrative human communication cultural
affordances
so these are absolutely topics that have
been addressed
although many of the earlier works are
like
here's people in the world
we're going to use active inference to
model it
but then
there's so much more
beyond that it's almost like a 1950s
cybernetics book
well we can just imagine that the person
is going to be involved in this feedback
loop
yeah but then that's not the the end of
the discussion on that um ali and then
john
uh i just wanted to mention that uh
well fep can potentially be
applied to any dynamical system with
ergodicity and uh because you see uh
in any system with the ergotic behavior
have uh some points of attraction some
attractors that
all the other states are converging to
so
it's pretty general and well
almost uh all dynamical systems we know
of
on different time scales
can be potentially
modeled with fep and as its corollary
with active inference
thank you that's the key point right
because that's that's what we look at
there got to your god ethnicity tough
word for me
um and and you can actually look at that
even in the context of
businesses business strategy and so
forth with uh some understanding of the
absorbing barriers right
when when does a business dissipate when
it's not close enough to its preferred
state
like adequate cash flow so um yeah so
that i think that that just seems like a
really interesting progression from
where the state of the art of dynamic
non-linear dynamic systems is the way we
model businesses now
so well that's the way some of us do it
a lot of people use a spreadsheet but
um
this would just seem like a potentially
tremendous advantage
yeah and then just a few notes then john
um this stephen fox who's also joined on
and talked about industrial engineering
he's recently
had this paper come out just a couple
days ago
and ironically a spreadsheet is provided
in this paper but this is also in
practice in several places in the world
in startup ecosystems
and it's very active influenced and then
one other more conceptual note um cad
cad which is the complex systems
modeling software and i know some of you
are involved in cad cad learning as well
they describe it as a language for
encoding generalized dynamical systems
and that is what it is
active block friends is our
project where jacob has done much of the
initial work that is implementing active
inference in cad cad and we have a whole
litany of questions
about the relationships between base
graphs generalized dynamical systems
variational inference
cad cad which takes more of like a
sampling based approach
versus the variational approaches that
we're discussing here in active
and
it's going to be very interesting as
this
systems engineering complex systems
simulation
as well as tokenomic and other things
becomes integrated with this analytical
framework especially if we can
demonstrate a true concordance between
active inference and gds
john
uh lyle i just wanted to say your your
comments are really spot on earlier
comments
uh you had i think if i can paraphrase
you had essentially said
maybe even a dysfunctional society is
performing active inference
and then and then that would lead us to
the
really to the the key components then of
that society or that social system is
what is its set of preferred states and
where is it placing its attention so if
the if the if a uh say an elite group of
very wealthy people or powerful people
are running the world and they're
running it for their preferences which
is to maintain their wealth and to and
to ensure that
that they stay on top well then the
world they could be performing
functional active inference and the
world could you know
could uh
could uh you know suffer the the
problems that that kind of system would
offer
on the other hand if in a highly
democratic system if people understand
that they want clean air and clean water
and peace and all that kind of stuff
and then that's their set of preferred
states and their attention is on that
and they're performing active influence
in
thank you john
um lyle and then mike
i would just throw uh so john i'm
completely
on board with that i would i would just
amplify a little bit on that i would say
to a certain extent preferences
and societal decisions are
emergent
so you you aren't going to find too many
people in the world are going to say
they want to be
you know starving or have war whatever
right and yet we do
so
the the interesting thing is how to me
is how does the
individual
you know i mean this is the the whole
build up right how does the individual
behavior somehow
uh
you create an emergent system that has
many bad outcomes
even though potentially none of those
are bad actors some of them are bad
actors but let's just take the the the
simple case there are no bad actors yet
we get bad outcomes why is that
and we can observe that in
existing systems and then we can ask the
question well
you know why is that and then maybe if
we understand why that is maybe we can
do something
to improve yes
great
um point and then just a short note
there was in our remote teams
we framed communication and information
architectures as organizational
affordances so
that could assist with decision making
find alignment where people do have
similar preferences like a zone of
proximate agreement in a negotiation
context
it might be broader but no matter how
broad it is if you can't forage the path
to it
it's going to be a failing system
mike
yeah i just want to add i think scaling
or the scale factor is
hugely important here so
uh if we're talking about interactions
amongst a handful of individuals we're
going to see different behaviors and
outcomes than
we might see on a global scale of
cultural interaction
okay and then the last comment on that
john deal for it
if your hand's still up i don't hear you
actually okay
your microphone may have changed or can
other people hear john
no okay um eric go for it
yeah how does this all apply to a highly
distributed system
i don't see that
yes
like a society is
good question the multi-agent case
is something that hasn't been studied
across the board but in 2021 with
colleagues we
made this is like one of the early
it's not the first multi-agent
simulation because there were
multi-agent simulations however it was
the first
active inference model involving
stigmergy which is the feedback process
with agents modifying their environments
and so on
we can think about even a nested
distributed
cognitive system as
inheriting some sparsity from a causal
perspective like there's more
connections in the base graph within the
nestmate's head as we're modeling it and
then interactions induce like a sparsity
between two brains and then they're
always coupled with the environment and
so on
and
that sparsity is a statistical
convenience but also it allows
factorizability of models and
the models may be factorized in a way
where
free energy calculations
could be for example
summed within a level of collective
behavior
i don't know if that's going it's not
that's not the solution in and of itself
to the modeling
but when we have systems of like nested
markov blankets
in closing systems and closing systems
and then also lateral interactions and
interfaces like collective behavior
those systems are at least amenable
to this kind of principled composition
via their sparsity
which does map onto a causal
architecture or at least a useful one of
the real world
so also remains to be seen
but i think that's a very important
question
um
lyle
yeah i would throw it eric i would throw
in on that that question because
society of course broadly speaking is
loosely coupled however of course there
are clicks and densely coupled areas
that are you know to create the well
under well documented complex connection
graphs right
so that connection graph is emergent
right so the question is i mean i think
this would be actually a really
fascinating research project
can we show that fep would generate
connection graphs or patterns the
of
societal interactions similar to what
has been observed right so there's lots
and lots of research on
what those graphs look like
so it is it possible for us to or
someone to
to
use fep to show how those kind of
connection patterns
would
emerge i think that's a really
interesting question
yes how we threshold
and
parameterize those causal graphs
how we evaluate counterfactuals on those
graphs
and that's related to the problem of
structure learning
but bayesian model selection
and other sort of hierarchical bayesian
methods
have the tools there
also just quick pointer to the project
ideas table
there's some very interesting projects
that people have suggested
jakub no big deal
sounds like a good one
but we can absolutely do it and that's
one of the advantages of being in like
an active and activity driven
participatory research and education
space is we're hopefully going to be
able to help each other
identify those projects and where their
hazard hasn't been overlap
and then scaffold those projects support
them and then provide them like a place
to communicate about the project
playing into the ontology active block
for ins
all these pieces that
one researcher working by themselves
would have
just
not those affordances
let's just try to quickly look at the
last several questions
so
um
must all preferred states and strategies
be ultimately linked to survival in some
way or in the case of some organisms can
free energy be related to something
other than survival
so
just a quick thought on that in the
context of repeated measurements
yes
survival is the capacity for repeated
measurements
free energies for
domain specific models can be made that
have nothing to do with survival
and i don't think that there's any
contradiction there
john
i still don't hear you actually
uh rohan and then anyone else who raises
their hand
yeah hi
uh so i was actually wondering because
uh
there's no treatment of time in any of
these uh methods right
so i
so
like is there any
accommodation made so if you're sampling
something
let's say you sample at a minute
frequency
you're getting a certain set of events
whereas if you're sampling at a much
higher frequency you would get a very
different much more noisy
data set but that might be essential to
capture certain things that might
actually enable survival maybe there's
certain events that act only at certain
times
so uh
from the perspective of
repeated measurement right so i think
free energy principle as it relates to
survival
uh could it just be related to some sort
of
creating an internal clock
for repeated measurement
great question
yes so far it's been almost
time independent as you suggest
but
we're going to be dealing with two
ways to deal with time in chapter four
and beyond and that's like a discrete
time formalization
where future and past states are
explicitly modeled partially observable
markov decision process
and then also a continuous time variance
where future and past time points are
not explicitly modeled however a taylor
series approximation
higher and higher derivatives of a
function are utilized to glean an
approximation to the future behavior of
a function those are two different ways
of dealing with time and then you talked
about like sampling rate
and
i think uh
you'll see many connections
and ways to apply that
for example you could imagine like if
the sensor is every seconds but you're
able to think 10 times per seconds
or what about when the sensor is every
10 seconds but you're only able to think
over this time scale
and it's those kinds of situations where
actually the frequencies are happening
differently
that we also might be able to address
yes rohan
uh yeah yeah also like if there are
multiple sensors some of them react
quickly some of them react slowly or if
there's just
uh
or if we look at active inference as
some sort of
model averaging phenomena right so you
have a model that runs really fast
that reacts really quickly and produces
predictions really quickly
and the other one
uh
acts more slowly
would those be
valid targets in
in any sense
yes i think it's a very um interesting
question i'll just add it here just
because it was where we were discussing
it um
like about different time scales
and the way that
cognitive clock rates for example and
sensory clock rates and then the time
scale events the statistical
regularities in the world happen
um
in model stream 4.1 with
devry's and colleagues
they talked about the message passing in
a factor graph so
any time that there's a base graph
there's a way to accomplish variational
inference on that base graph using
message passing techniques
that's what their package is about
forney lab
and then what they hinted at towards the
end is actually this reactive message
passing
development which uses reactive
programming techniques so whereas in
message passing at least in the forney
factor graph formalization it's like you
crank the model and a message is passed
amongst every node or there's like a
given execution order of messages that
are passed for the entire graph
however the reactive
message passing paradigm
may allow like
uncoupling of the frequency of message
passing
so you might have one prior that gets
one message per hour and then there's
another distribution that gets one
message per minute and another one is
getting one per second
and even that one could be doing model
averaging of something much faster
so there's there's many ways that i
think your questions will be starting to
be explored rohan and then john
okay john if you're like
can you hear me now oh good
on the question of survival i think you
would have to identify to answer it
you'd have to identify first what is the
organism or what is the agent that
you're talking about because obviously
as if it's an individual person a person
might uh sacrifice their life for others
so then you know survival is not the
main necessarily the main uh
driver
but if it's a society
then
you know that's a
that any individual might not survive
but society as a whole might i suspect
in the bigger picture that it's not
it's not really survival of a species
it's probably
the ability to um
the propagation of information somehow
that's what i would guess in the in the
biggest picture
that's probably what everything is doing
is propagating information
and mike levin has also explored like
how changes in the scope of the self
can lead to like an organism with
reduced fitness as a function of a
cancer with increased fitness and
vision so to speak and so like just
because there's an imperative or
normative way that we model behavior
doesn't mean that everything works or
anything like that
yes
ali
yes adding to what john said well
yes again i believe here survival
doesn't necessarily mean
biological survival and
actually it means it it has a much
broader sense
and uh it means
uh
the existence of things actually it's a
metaphysical concept here because um
as i said
carl priston has
defined the existence or the the the
requisites of
[Music]
the prerequisites of existence as uh
having two uh parameters or two features
uh namely uh being an ergotic system and
having markup blankets so any system uh
which has
these any system which has these two
properties can basically be considered
uh as an existence system or
we can call it a surviving system here
just to in our last minutes before we go
to tools
touch on some of these points can markup
blanket be considered a decoupling
mechanism
so can anything mathematical be
considered a mechanism
people use terms in different ways so
just to raise the point that like a
linear aggression on height and weight
isn't a mechanism of height and weight
it's just a descriptor so markov blanket
doesn't need to be any kind of mechanism
at all it doesn't need to cut nature at
the joints or anything like that that
being said there are ways in which one
could think of the blanket again
variously depending on how the real
generative model and generative process
separated as part of a markov partition
sometimes there's ways to think of it as
how they're coupled
other times it is a statistical
decoupling of a type
it's a partial information encapsulation
but it's not a total encapsulation
and that way it is like an interface and
yes thanks to whomever has added this
quote
um
this is one reason why the transcripts
of all of the live streams and
discussions augmented with the ontology
will be so helpful and searchable
because we could find sentences that
have raised similar points
and addressed them so good question
and then just last ones
um
maybe we can come back
to this
and then um
this one is a a nice next step
question thinking about friction what is
the analogy to friction in a cognitive
system
what is what is the stochastic
fluctuation
on our cognitive path of least action
what is that in the real world realism
ontological claims
and then
from the behavioral modeling perspective
where are we using these equations
and
partitioning variants
into
a path or a flow of least action
and a variable that is analogous to
stochastic fluctuation or friction
but doesn't take on any of the baggage
of describing some feature or component
or mechanism of the physical system
so also a great question though and
we'll leave this one in case people want
to continue to address it
so
that brings us to the end of chapter
three live meetings
next week we'll head into two weeks of
chapter four
then two weeks of chapter five
and then we'll have two weeks to sort of
ground ourselves think about what we've
learned talk about project ideas and
then we'll be heading into the second
cohort of the first half of the book
and for those who are here who want to
continue
into
the the back nine as it were the second
half of the textbook
and also people are welcomed and
encouraged to be facilitators or return
participants in the second cohort first
part because it's many coats of paint
for everyone and so we want to provide
that affordance to return again and
again and again
because the basics are the classics and
the essence and the seed of innovation
all this other important things that
happen when we return and clarify
also we've had to sort of do all of
these entering the figures and equations
for the first time
but now that we have the architecture
people can focus on annotating them or
they can focus on adding new questions
or improving the questions that others
have written
if anyone else has any comments that
they want to
make while the recording is still
occurring i'll just give a few seconds
for anyone to raise their hand
um and then we'll end this session
and then take a one minute break and
then in this room we'll be continuing on
with tools organizational unit
and um if you want to continue speaking
with people here about just any topic at
all you can head up to a room up top and
then of course always you can join into
the discord voice channels and just be
working on things like during the math
reading group or any other area rohan
and then anyone else who raises their
hand
yeah so i actually so sorry for this
late thought so i i'm just curious is so
when you say the free energy principle
it's basically figuring out some
set point of states internal states that
you that the agent wants to be with
right it's not necessary that
it actually couples to the real world so
why wouldn't it be that
okay it just becomes a brain in the vat
type of situation
so it does so it just find needs to find
the set point that helps it survive
so
it doesn't have to actually model the
real world it just has to find a place
and
no matter what happens just stay there
so it's not
really dynamic it is that could be
is that a possibility
it is dynamic it is explicitly modeling
time and one can make a model just like
a linear regression could be static or
you could use the linear
regression technique and use it in
i was i was more referring it uh so uh
if you look at some of the reinforcement
deep reinforcement learning models right
they usually find some trick within the
game like if you're looking at atari
games and you say maximize the score for
example
so it tries to find
uh you know okay i can maximize the
score by doing the simplest thing that
doesn't require me to progress in any
way
but
it would increase the score
okay
so um
yes these are important things so write
them down so that we can have infinite
discourse on them
um
the brain the vat does still have an
interface with the environment whether
it's receive only and then you brought
up like it doesn't have to be like
modeling the quote real world
this is the architecture that helps us
bypass
that
and say right the particulate states the
particular states which are the blanket
states and the internal states
are doing inference acting as if they're
doing inference on external states
so it's perfectly compatible with
scientific realism scientific surrealism
aesthetic surrealism
you could but so i mean the states could
be hallucinating
it could be hallucinating the world and
it's actually just
doing inference on the hallucination
rather than
actual reality as such
anil seth and many others who speak of
that uh reality as a controlled
hallucination they're they're two feet
in that territory without any qualms
and feeling like it addresses questions
that have been unaddressed by other
perspectives
okay okay yeah okay so i'll just put
this down yep cool
thank you everybody